Guide to the ACLU of Ohio Kent State Project Records
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
ACLU of Ohio Kent State Project records
1960-1980
MS 1800
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
62.2
Records of ACLU of Ohio attorneys document preparation for the retrial of Krause v. Rhodes in 1978. Because the retrial was the culmination of a long, difficult legal battle for accountability in the deaths of four students and the injury of nine others, the collection includes not just materials assembled specifically for the 1978 trial, but also materials gathered for previous lawsuits related to the May 4th, 1970, shootings at Kent State University. The collection includes documents filed in various courts such as briefs, memoranda and motions, transcripts of trial proceedings, and depositions. It also includes materials produced by the attorneys and their staff, such as correspondence, research memoranda, legal stragety communications, and witness files of individuals who testified at one or more trials.
American Civil Liberties Union of Ohio
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of the ACLU of Ohio, 2006.
The ACLU of Ohio Kent State Project records appear to have been promised to Yale just after the 1979 settlement. The attorneys and the families were concerned that if the materials were deposited with a quasi-governmental organization such as the Ohio Historical Society, they might be mishandled or manipulated, thus endangering the historical record -- so great was the distrust of government officials after the protracted legal battle for justice.
The materials had been stored in a Columbus, Ohio office for some years, and in 1995 the ACLU of Ohio staff had no record of the fact that the records had been promised to Yale. That year the files were deposited at Princeton University, the official repository of the national American Civil Liberties Union. After the previous arrangement came to light, the records were shipped from Princeton to Yale in 2002, and a formal deed of gift was signed in 2006.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Original audiovisual materials, as well as preservation and duplicating masters, may not be played. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist must pay for a use copy, which is retained by the repository. Researchers wishing to obtain an additional copy for their personal use should consult Copying Services information on the Manuscripts and Archives web site.
Related Material
Kent State Collection (MS 804), Manuscripts and Archives, Yale University Library.
Arrangement
Arranged in three series: I. Legal Documents, 1970-1980. II. Attorney Work Product, 1970-1980. III. Background Materials, circa 1960-1979.
Scope and Contents
Records of ACLU of Ohio attorneys document preparation for the retrial of Krause v. Rhodes in 1978. Because the retrial was the culmination of a long, difficult legal battle for accountability in the deaths of four students and the injury of nine others, the collection includes not just materials assembled specifically for the 1978 trial, but also materials gathered for previous lawsuits related to the May 4th shootings.The collection includes documents filed in various courts such as briefs, memoranda and motions, transcripts of trial proceedings, and depositions. It also includes materials produced by the attorneys and their staff, such as correspondence, research memoranda, legal stragety communications, and witness files of individuals who testified at one or more trials.
A particular strength of the collection is two sets of interview transcripts prepared by the ACLU of Ohio, one set from 1970 and another from 1975. In 1970, individuals were interviewed about civil liberties violations they might have observed before, during, and after the May 4th, 1970 shootings. The 1975 interviews appear to have been conducted to gather additional eyewitness information in preparation for the 1975 civil trial. Finally, the collection includes a considerable amount of background material gathered from a variety of sources, such as investigative agencies, the media, Kent State University, and other parties interested in the events surrounding the May 4th shootings.
Biographical / Historical
The American Civil Liberties Union, founded in 1920, works to defend the individual rights guaranteed by the Constitution and laws of the United States. While local ACLU chapters formed as early as 1921, a statewide Ohio ACLU affiliate was not formed until 1951. The statewide group remained a relatively small, unincorporated grassroots organization over the next two decades. The organization drew its influence as much from its local chapters as from its national and state groups.
Benson Wolman had just been hired as the state organization's executive director when four students were killed by the National Guard at Kent State University on May 4th, 1970. The National Guard had been called to the Kent campus to disperse a protest against Nixon's incursion into Cambodia. At 12:24 pm, a group of Guardsman turned together towards the students and fired about 60 rounds into the crowd. Four students were killed and nine others were disabled or injured. Twenty-nine guards admitted firing.
Within days of the deaths of Sandra Scheuer, Jeffrey Miller, Allison Krause, and William Schroeder, the Kent Chapter of the ACLU deployed volunteers to interview witnesses about possible civil liberties violations that may have taken place before, during and after the May 4th disturbance. The national ACLU and Ohio affiliate joined together to form the Kent State Project, not just to redress the constitutional violations suffered by the victims of the shootings, but also those experienced by other students and community members as a result of the disturbance. The United Methodist Church also provided support and funds for the case. For instance, the ACLU intervened in the following situations where constitutional rights were violated:
The dorm rooms of 8,500 students were searched without warrants days after the shootings (Morgan v. Hayth).
Students and university officials were ordered by county judges not to publicly discuss a state grand jury report, violating their free speech rights (King v. Jones).
A ban on student voting in academic communities was overturned (Fridrich v. Brown).
Local officials tried to deny needy students the right to food stamps.
Student groups were infiltrated by undercover agents in an attempt to entrap them, which involved unlawful surveillance and an invasion of privacy (VVAW v. Fyke).
Limitations were sought on the use of deadly force, premature use of troops and nonarrest detentions (Morgan v. Rhodes, sub. Nom. Gilligan v. Morgan).
At the same time, the national ACLU and the Ohio affiliate offered legal representation to the victims. Sarah and Martin Scheuer, the parents of Sandra Scheuer, retained the ACLU as legal counsel, and the case became captioned Scheuer v. Rhodes (James Rhodes was Ohio's governor at the time). Other victims subsequently retained private attorneys, including the Krause family.
In the years that followed a number of investigations, grand juries and trials were undertaken, none of which resulted in a determination of accountability for the shootings. Attorneys for the Guardsmen argued that the individual Guardsmen were personally immune from civil charges because they were acting in their capacity as state officials. The attorneys for the families argued, however, that the Guardsmen had violated the victims' constitutional rights by depriving them of their due process rights: in essence, that they were killed or injured by government officials without being charged with or convicted of any crime. The case Scheuer v. Rhodes reached the U.S. Supreme Court, which decided that the Guardsmen could be sued as individuals. A victory in Scheuer v. Rhodes turned out to be a pivotal legal milestone, for it allowed a civil suit for damages against the National Guardsmen to go forward.
The pressure to pursue redress in a civil suit heightened when the National Guardsmen were exonerated in a criminal trial, U.S. v. Shafer, in 1974. The U.S. Supreme Court decision in Scheuer v. Rhodes that same year allowed the families to pursue a civil suit. A district court consolidated the families' lawsuits, and the merged case, captioned Krause v. Rhodes, reached trial in the spring of 1975. ACLU attorneys joined with the private attorneys to argue wrongful death and injury. A jury found in favor of the Guardsmen, and the victims and their attorneys appealed to the U.S. Supreme Court arguing that a number of procedural and jury instruction errors prevented a fair trial. The Supreme Court acknowledged the errors, and sent the case back for retrial. The ACLU agreed to take on the appeal of this decision, and the trial began in late December 1978. The case was argued by ACLU attorney Sanford J. Rosen. After only a few days in court, the parties agreed to a settlement, in which the Guardsmen agreed to sign a "statement of regret," and $675,000 in damages was distributed among the victims and their families. Attorneys' fees were also awarded.
The settlement was controversial. Some felt a better resolution could have been reached, or that allowing the trial to reach a jury again could have produced a finding against the Guardsmen, while others felt that the settlement closed the door on a tragic time in our nation's history. In the words of the family in the statement they issued after the settlement was reached: "The State of Ohio although protected by the doctrine of sovereign immunity and consequently not legally responsible in a technical sense, has now recognized its responsibility by paying a substantial amount of money in damages for the injuries and deaths caused by the shootings."
Kent State Shootings, Kent, Ohio, 1970; American Civil Liberties Union of Ohio; Kent State University -- Students
- Legal Documents, 1970-1980; Series I
  Scope and Contents
  This series consists of court documents prepared in litigation related to the May 4th, 1970 shootings at Kent State University. Included are depositions, briefs, motions, memoranda, affidavits, and exhibits. Transcripts of court proceedings are included for some of the lawsuits as well. The bulk of the material consists of a fairly complete set of legal documents filed in the civil trial, Krause v. Rhodes, in 1975, the appeals in 1977-1978, and the retrial, which commenced in late 1978.
  Also included in the series are incomplete sets of court documents from other litigation related to the Kent State shootings, such as the criminal trial against the National Guardsmen, U.S. v. Shafer, and individual suits filed by victims' family members, such as Scheuer v. Rhodes, which was eventually consolidated with Krause v. Rhodes.
  The best place to begin researching the legal proceedings is with the pleadings binders, which attorneys assemble in reverse chronological order to track all activity on a case. All court filings are typically included, and sometimes relevant correspondence. Well organized pleadings binders, with indices in the front of each binder, are included for the civil trial in Krause v. Rhodes (1974-1976), the Krause v. Rhodes appeal to the Sixth Circuit Court of Appeals (1976-1977), and the Krause v. Rhodes retrial (1978-1979). Pleadings binders are also included for Scheuer v. Rhodes (1970-1973).
  An incomplete set of exhibits is included at the end of the series. Paper documents are arranged by exhibit number. Some exhibit items--such as audiotapes, bullets, and books--are housed separately. It is unclear whether the items were actually introduced at trial, and if so, in which court. Other items marked as exhibits appear in other series in the collection.
  The series is arranged by case name, and therein broadly by document type. Materials for the Krause v. Rhodes trials are arranged chronologically following the progression of the trial, appeals, and retrial.
  - Krause v. Rhodes civil trial (United States District Court for the Nothern District of Ohio, Eastern Division No. C-70-544)
    - Pleadings binders, including list of individual pleadings inside front cover of each binder
      - Book I (1-88), 1970-1974 (Box 1)
      - Book II (89-144), 1974-1975 (Box 1)
      - Book III (145-181), 1975 (Box 2)
      - Book IV (182-229), 1975 (Box 2)
      - Book V (230-263), 1975 (Box 3)
      - Book VI (264-270), 1975-1976 (Box 3)
    - Appendix (Volume 11 is sealed by court order and was retained by the donor), 1976
      - Volume 1: Litigation documents (Box 3)
      - Volume 2: Transcript (Box 3)
      - Volumes 3-5: Transcript (Box 4)
      - Volumes 6-8: Transcript (Box 5)
      - Volume 9: Exhibits (Box 6)
      - Volume 10: Photographs (Box 6)
      - Volume 12: Testimony and exhibits (Box 6)
    - Court documents
      - Circa 1974-1976, 4 folders (Box 6)
      - 1975-1976, 5 folders (Box 7)
      - 1976-1977, 2 folders (Box 8)
    - Voir dire of the jury, 4 volumes, 1975 (Box 8)
    - Charge to the jury, plaintiffs' proposed revisions, 1975 (Box 8)
    - Closing arguments, Joe Kelner, 1975 (Box 8)
    - Depositions, individually bound
      - Raymond James Srp, Charles R. Fassinger, Myron P. Pryor, Harry D. Jones, 1971-1974 (Box 9)
      - John W. Simons, Richard Lobo, William Feest, Alan Canfora, Dean Richard Kahler, James A. Rhodes, Charles Ayers, Howard Edward Ruffner, 1974 (Box 10)
      - William Albert Ling, John Darnell, John Merrick McElroy, James Laurenson, Sylvester DelCorso, Robert H. Canterbury, 1974 (Box 11)
      - Raymond James Srp, John E. Martin, James A. Rhodes, Dennis L. Breckenridge, Rodney Biddle, Colonel Arthur E. Wallach, LeRoy M. Satrom, 1974-1975 (Box 12)
      - William B. Shimp, Jr., Robert Duane Maxwell, James F. Devoll, John E. McElroy, William J. McManus, James Edward Pierce, William E. Perkins, Dana Stewart, Leon Smith, 1975 (Box 13)
      - Edith Wiencek, Lucy DeLeone, Colonel Sylvester T. DelCorso, Barry W. Morris, James D. McGee, Lawrence A. Shafer, Ralph W. Zoller, James Ronald Snyder, 1975 (Box 14)
      - Robert Edward Matson (deposition transcript missing first 3 pages), James Russell, Dr. David Allen Ambler, Donald E. Manly, Jr., William James Chase, Arthur S. Krause, Robert B. Krupansky, Dale L. Antram, 1975 (Box 15)
      - Richard D. Lutey, Sarah Scheuer, Dr. Robert I. White, William Herschler, Lloyd W. Thomas, Jr., Paul Petrella, Robert Hart, Roger A. Maas, James W. Farriss, Joseph Dale Sholl, Ronnie B. Myers, Russell E. Repp, 1975 (Box 16)
      - Larry Mowrer, Phillip D. Raber, Richard R. Shade, Lonnie Dean Hinton, Roy W. Dew, Dwight G. Cline, John E. Martin, Frank Haas, Gordon R. Bedall, Thomas Kelley, David Lee Snure, Wayne Oakes, 1975 (Box 17)
      - Charles Joseph Barnette, Paul Reynolds Naujoks, David Rogers, Robert F. Thompson, Ronald Joseph West, Paul Richard Zimmerman, Rudy Morris, Harry D. Jones, J. Gordon Peltier, Terrance Norman, 1975 (Box 18)
      - Dr. Robert White, Norman Minner Rich, M.D., John R. Cleary, James F. Ahern, Edward L. King, 1975 (Box 19)
    - Transcripts
      - Volume 1 (volume 2 is missing), 1975 May 27 (Box 20)
      - Volume 2 addendum, 1975 May 28 (Box 20)
      - Volumes 3-5, 1975 May 29-June 3 (Box 20)
      - Volumes 6-8, 1975 June 4-9 (Box 21)
      - Volumes 9-11, 1975 June 10-12 (Box 22)
      - Volumes 12-14, 1975 June 16-18 (Box 23)
      - Volume 15 -17, 1975 June 19-24 (Box 24)
      - Volume 18-20, 1975 June 25-30 (Box 25)
      - Volume 21-23, 1975 July 1-7 (Box 26)
      - Volume 24-26, 1975 July 8-10 (Box 27)
      - Volume 27-29, 1975 July 14-16 (Box 28)
      - Volume 30-32, 1975 July 17-22 (Box 29)
      - Volume 33-35, 1975 July 23-29 (Box 30)
      - Volume 36-39, 1975 July 30-August 5 (Box 31)
      - Volume 40-42, 1975 August 6-11 (Box 32)
      - Volume 43-46, 1975 August 12-18 (Box 33)
      - Volume 47-49, 1975 August 19-21 (Box 34)
      - Volumes 50-51, 53 (volume 52 is missing), 1975 August 22-25 (Box 35)
  - Krause v. Rhodes civil trial appeals
    - United States Court of Appeals for the Sixth Circuit, No. 76-1095
      - Pleadings binders (labeled Books VII-VIII), 2 volumes, 1976-1977 (Box 35)
      - Court documents
        - 1976-1977, 5 folders (Box 36)
        - 1977-1980, 3 folders (Box 37)
    - United States Supreme Court, October Term, court documents, 2 folders, 1977 (Box 37)
  - Krause v. Rhodes retrial
    - Pleadings binders
      - Book 1, contains no list of individual pleadings, 1978 (Box 37)
      - Books 2-3, including list of individual pleadings in each binder, 1978 (Box 38)
    - Court documents
      - 1978-1979, 2 folders (Box 38)
      - 1978-1979, 5 folders (Box 39)
      - 1979, 3 folders (Box 40)
    - Proceedings
      - Volumes 1-2, 1978 October-November (Box 40)
      - Volumes 3-8, 1978 November-1979 January (Box 41)
    - Settlement pleadings, 1979 (Box 42)
    - Depositions of Paul Locher, Lt. Gen. Walter G. Johnson, and Alan M. Canfora, 3 bound volumes, 1978 (Box 42)
    - Other materials related to Krause v. Rhodes, 3 folders, 1970-1974 (Box 42)
    - Krause v. Rhodes, additional briefs, depositions, and proceedings, 3 folders, 1975-1978 (Box 86)
  - Materials relating to other trials
    - CBS v. Don Young, pleadings binder and other materials, 2 folders, 1975 (Box 43)
    - Scheuer v. Rhodes, 2 folders, 1970-1975 (Box 43)
    - Scheuer v. Rhodes, 3 folders, 1970-1975 (Box 44)
    - Hammond v. Brown, court documents and transcripts, 3 folders, 1970-1971 (Box 45)
    - Hammond v. Brown, court documents and transcripts, 1970-1971 (Box 46)
    - Ohio v. Rupe, transcripts, 2 folders, 1971 (Box 46)
    - U.S. v. Shafer
      - Hearings on motions, 1974 (Box 46)
      - Hearings on motions, 3 folders, 1974 (Box 47)
      - Transcript, 1974 (Box 47)
      - Transcript, 1974 (Box 48)
      - Court documents, 3 folders, 1974 (Box 48)
      - Witness list, 1974 (Box 48)
  - Other legal documents relating to the Kent State Project
    - Court documents, not Krause v. Rhodes, related to Kent State trials, 2 folders, circa 1973-1977 (Box 49)
    - Court documents, 1970-1977 (Box 49)
    - King v. Jones, grand jury gag order, 2 folders, circa 1970-1971 (Box 49)
    - Affidavits, 1975-1979 (Box 50)
    - Portions of transcripts, depositions, and proceedings, 3 folders, circa 1970-1979 (Box 50)
  - Exhibits and evidence, 5 folders, circa 1970-1979 (Box 51)
  - Exhibits and evidence, includes spent shell casings, 5 folders, circa 1970-1979 (Box 52)
  - Oversize exhibits, diagrams and overviews of site of May 4th, 1970, shootings, 6 items, circa 1970-1975 (Box 188–189)
  - Exhibits, audiovisual materials (titles taken from labels on materials)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Original audiovisual materials, as well as preservation and duplicating masters, may not be played. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist must pay for a use copy, which is retained by the repository. Researchers wishing to obtain an additional copy of non-commercially produced items for their personal use should consult the ordering reproductions information on the Manuscripts and Archives web site.
    - Sunday night, direct and filtered tracks, 1970 May; 1 (Box 120)
      - Use copy, 1 (Box 120U)
    - Sunday night, 1970 May; audiocassette (Box 121)
      - Use copy, 2 (Box 121Ua–121Ub)
    - Events, including shooting incident at KSU, 1970 May 4; 1 (Box 122)
      - Use copy, 1 (Box 122U)
    - Sunday evening and Monday activities beginning with Bell; Monday sequence ends with shooting, 1970 May 3-4; 1 (Box 123)
      - Use copy, 1 (Box 123U)
    - Governor Rhodes' press conference, 1970 May; 1 (Box 124)
      - Use copy, 1 (Box 124U)
    - Narrative tape,, 2 audiotapes, 1970 (Box 125–126)
    - CBS outtakes (silent) [commercially-produced], 1970; 1 (Box 127)
      - Use copy, 1 (Box 127U)
    - Plaintiff's exhibit 50013/Defendant's exhibit R-1 ("Breckinridge-Head" written on leader), circa 1970; film reel (16mm) (Box 128)
    - Recording from record in 1971 Chestnut Burr, audiocassette (Box 129)
    - May 3 demands/in news car; May 4 before shots, 1970 May; audiocassette (Box 130)
      - Use copy, 3 (Box 130Ua–130Uc)
- Attorney Work Product, 1970-1980; Series II
  This series includes legal strategy materials gathered by attorneys, correspondence, two sets of alphabetically arranged witness files, and transcripts of interviews conducted by ACLU staff and volunteers in 1970 and 1975.
  The witness files were created on individuals who testified in the 1975 civil trial, Krause v. Rhodes. The files contain one or more of the following documents: summaries and originals of depositions, trial testimony, Federal Bureau of Investigation interview reports (FBI Form 302), National Guard interview statements, Ohio State Highway Patrol interview statements, and handwritten statements. Some files also contain summaries of special grand jury and federal grand jury testimony. Some of these items are marked as exhibits.
  The ACLU interviews (Groups 1-3) were conducted in 1970 to gather information about constitutional rights violations arising from events leading up to, during, and following the May 4, 1970 shootings. Interviewees were asked to trace their movements over those days, and to describe any civil liberties violations they observed, including parties involved, location, day and time, and the circumstances. An partial list of interviewees, created by the ACLU and somewhat difficult to follow, is included.
  Additional interviews were conducted in 1975, presumably to develop strategy for the appeal of the civil trial decision. Interviewees were asked about the general chronology of the events around May 4, 1970, specifically regarding the beginning of the student rally, the National Guard's and students' activities on the practice field, and the march up Blanket Hill. Interviewees were also asked to describe their thoughts about the shooting, the aftermath, and their observations about why they thought it happened. Most of these interviews are handwritten on forms and legal paper.
  Legal strategy materials contain memoranda, research summaries, and notes on witness and trial preparations. Folders of correspondence are also included, organized by year, including incoming and outgoing items as well copies of correspondence not directly involving parties to the litigation. Letters protected by attorney-client privilege have been removed by the ACLU of Ohio.
  The series is arranged by broad types of material.
  - Strategy memoranda and notes
    - 1970-1975, 7 folders (Box 53)
    - 1975-1978, 7 folders (Box 54)
    - 1979 (Box 55)
    - Circa 1970-1980, 4 folders (Box 55)
    - Circa 1970-1980, 16 folders (Box 56)
  - Jury selection instructions, and opening statements, 1974-1977 (Box 57)
  - Newspaper clippings relating to the case, 1971-1975 (Box 57)
  - Deposition testimony and exhibits, circa 1974-1975 (Box 57)
  - Correspondence
    - 1970-1973, 4 folders (Box 57)
    - 1974-1978, 5 folders (Box 58)
    - 1978-1980, 4 folders (Box 59)
    - From the United Methodist Church, 1971-1978 (Box 59)
  - Witness files, set 1, circa 1970-1978
    - Bambeck, John, 2 folders (Box 59)
    - Berns, Ellis (Box 60)
    - Biddle, Rodney, 2 folders (Box 60)
    - Bishop, Joy (Box 60)
    - Breckenridge, Dennis (Box 60)
    - Brill, Charles (Box 60)
    - Brown, James (Box 60)
    - Canfora, Alan, 2 folders (Box 60)
    - Canterbury, Robert, 3 folders (Box 61)
    - Cleary, John, 2 folders (Box 62)
    - Cline, Dwight, 2 folders (Box 62)
    - Darnell, John (Box 62)
    - Deegan, Charles (Box 62)
    - Delaney, Michael, 2 folders (Box 63)
    - DelCorso, Sylvester, 2 folders (Box 63)
    - Denton, Deborah (Box 64)
    - Denton, William (Box 64)
    - Dombrowsky (Box 64)
    - Fallon, Howard (Box 64)
    - Farriss, James (Box 64)